<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Kyle M. Douglass (biology)</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link type="application/rss+xml" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/categories/biology.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2015 08:58:44 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Overcoming complexity in biology</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/overcoming-complexity-in-biology.html</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I've been sitting in on a short lecture series presented by &lt;a href="http://markolab.bmbcb.northwestern.edu/marko/"&gt;Prof. John
Marko&lt;/a&gt; here at the EPFL. The topic is on the biophysics of DNA and
covers what is probably at least a 25 year span of research that has
emerged on its mechanical and biochemical properties.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
DNA amazes me in two different ways: relatively simple physical
theories can explain &lt;i&gt;in vitro&lt;/i&gt; experiments, but establishing a
complete understanding of the behavior of DNA and its associated
proteins (collectively known as chromatin) &lt;i&gt;in vivo&lt;/i&gt; seems at this
point almost hopeless.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So why do I think it's so difficult to establish a complete physical
theory of the nucleus?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Certainly a lot of recent research has helped us to understand parts
of what happens inside the nucleus. Take for example recent
experiments that look at &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transcription_factor#Accessibility_of_DNA-binding_site"&gt;transcription factor&lt;/a&gt; (TF) binding and the
nuclear architecture. TF binding experiments have helped us understand
the mechanism of how a single transcription factor ``searches'' for a
target site on a chromosome. It undergoes diffusion in the crowded
nuclear environment, occasionally binding to the DNA non-specifically
and sliding along it. We now know that this combined diffusion/sliding
mechanism produces an optimum search strategy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Studies of nuclear architecture attempt to understand how the long DNA
polymer, which is on the order of &lt;i&gt;one meter&lt;/i&gt; long, is packaged into
the nucleus, which is only about &lt;i&gt;five micrometers&lt;/i&gt; in diameter. This
is nearly six orders of magnitude of compaction. Some current theories
treat the DNA as a hierarchically packaged polymer or a fractal
structure. Interestingly, the fractal model can &lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24380602"&gt;explain why TF's may
diffuse optimally&lt;/a&gt; and when crowding can hinder their search.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Both of these examples represent a generalization of one particular
phenomenon that occurs inside the nucleus. And even given the enormity
of these works, I think this generalization can be dubious because it
may not apply to all cell types and there may be differences between
cultured cells and those found in an actual organism.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The problem in capturing complete physical models of the nucleus seems
to lie with the philosophy of physics itself: find the most essential
parts of the system and include those in your model, discarding all
irrelevant details. Unfortunately, &lt;i&gt;in vitro&lt;/i&gt; experiments suggest that
every detail seems to matter inside the nucleus. Local salt
concentrations effect electrostatic interactions and entropic binding
between proteins and DNA, the global nuclear architecture has an
effect on single TF's diffusing inside the nucleus, there are a huge
number of proteins that associate with DNA and control the
conformation in &lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22495300"&gt;toplogically associating domains&lt;/a&gt;. The list goes on and
on.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A common theme to this list that I have described above is that
phenomena at one length scale tend to have a direct impact on those at
another, like the global nuclear architecture affecting a single TF
trajectory. These are hallmarks of complexity: a dependence on the
details of a system and multiscale behavior.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am currently of the opinion that a complete model of the nucleus,
and probably of other biological systems, must therefore necessarily
abandon one important part of physical theories: reduction to the
simplest possible set of parameters to describe a system. We need to
incorporate all the details across all length scales to reproduce what
exactly is going on.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And if classical physics falls short of this goal, what other
approaches do we then require?
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>biology</category><category>biophysics</category><category>complexity</category><guid>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/overcoming-complexity-in-biology.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2015 07:16:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The philosophy of -omics studies</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/omics.html</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
As a physcist, I'm a relative newcomer to the biological
sciences. As a result, many approaches to doing science within these
fields are new and really interesting to me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One such idea is the &lt;i&gt;-omics&lt;/i&gt; approach to science. Sonja Prohaska
and Peter Stadler provide an insightful and sometimes amusing
intrepetation of &lt;i&gt;-omics&lt;/i&gt; studies in an article in the book
&lt;i&gt;Bioinformatics for Omics Data.&lt;/i&gt; (The PubMed link to the article is
&lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21370084"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but you can find a pdf by Googling "The use and abuse of
-omes.") According to them, &lt;i&gt;-omics&lt;/i&gt; refers to the research field of
digesting the pile of data coming from measurements of a particular
&lt;i&gt;-ome&lt;/i&gt;, such as the "genome" or "transcriptome." The goal is to
relate the collection of parts within the &lt;i&gt;-ome&lt;/i&gt; to biological
function, or at least to determine function by comparing &lt;i&gt;-omes&lt;/i&gt; of
two different organisms.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The authors explain that &lt;i&gt;-omics&lt;/i&gt; approaches have three components,
which I quote from their article:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;&lt;li&gt;A suite of (typically high-throughput) technologies address a
well-defined collection of biological objects, the pertinent
&lt;i&gt;-ome&lt;/i&gt;.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Both technologically and conceptually there is a cataloging
effort to enumerate and characterize the individual
objects–hopefully coupled with an initiative to make this
catalog available as a database.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beyond the enumeration of objects, one strives to cover the
quantitative aspects of the &lt;i&gt;-ome&lt;/i&gt; at hand.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;
While grand in scope, these approaches carry difficulties that to me
appear unique. As stated above, &lt;i&gt;-omic&lt;/i&gt; information is acquired
through high-throughput techniques, which means that they generate
very large amounts of data. Of major concern is actually linking
this data to biological function. In other words, scientists must
answer whether the correlations in the data actually allow us to
predict the behavior of a cell or tissue. As might be expected,
generating a complex data set such as is found in &lt;i&gt;-omics&lt;/i&gt; studies
can be quite impressive at first glance. But this complexity may
hide the fact that no biologically relevant conclusions can be drawn
from it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The authors specifically enumerate four limitations that could
adversely affect &lt;i&gt;-omics&lt;/i&gt; studies:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;&lt;li&gt;Technical limitations
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Limitations in the experimental design (such as heavy reliance on
assumptions)
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conceptual limitations
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Limitations in the analysis
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Particularly, the conceptual limitations struck me as
intriguing. The authors offered the example of genomics studies in
which the notion of a "gene" is not currently a well-defined
concept. When the concepts underpinning an entire collection of
measurements is unclear, we should question whether the measured
data has the meaning that we think it does.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Overall, I found that this commentary provided an interesting and
sobering view of one particular approach to studying biology. It's
interesting because I suspect that many important biological
questions in the near future will come from taking an integrated and
systems perspective. This perspective will require high-throughput
techniques that carry the same limitations that &lt;i&gt;-omics&lt;/i&gt; studies
have.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>biology</category><guid>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/omics.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2014 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>