<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>Kyle M. Douglass (computing)</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/categories/computing.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2016 07:22:40 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Learning Python's Multiprocessing Module</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/learning-pythons-multiprocessing-module.html</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I've been doing a bit of programming work lately that would greatly
benefit from a speed boost using parallel/concurrent processing
tools. Essentially, I'm doing a &lt;a href="http://www.mathworks.com/help/simulink/examples/parallel-simulations-using-parfor-parameter-sweep-in-normal-mode.html"&gt;parameter sweep&lt;/a&gt; where the values for
two different simulation parameters are input into the simulation and
allowed to run with the results being recorded to disk at the end. The
point is to find out how the simulation results vary with the
parameter values.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In my current code, a new simulation is initialized with each pair of
parameter values inside one iteration of a for loop; each iteration of
the loop is independent of the others. Spreading these iterations over
the 12 cores on my workstation should result in about a 12x decrease
in the amount of time the simulation takes to run.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've had good success using the &lt;code&gt;parfor&lt;/code&gt; loop construct in Matlab in
the past, but my simulation was written in Python and I want to learn
more about Python's multiprocessing tools, so this post will explore
that module in the context of performing parameter sweeps.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;Profile the code first to identify bottlenecks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First, I profiled my code to identify where any slowdowns might be
occurring in the serial program. I used a great tutorial at the &lt;a href="https://zapier.com/engineering/profiling-python-boss/"&gt;Zapier
Engineering&lt;/a&gt; blog to write a decorator for profiling the main instance
method of my class that was doing most of the work. Surprisingly, I
found that a few numpy methods were taking the most time, namely
&lt;b&gt;norm()&lt;/b&gt; and &lt;b&gt;cross()&lt;/b&gt;. To address this, I directly imported the
Fortran BLAS &lt;b&gt;nrm2()&lt;/b&gt; function using scipy's &lt;b&gt;get_blas_funcs()&lt;/b&gt;
function and hard-coded the cross product in pure Python inside the
method; these two steps alone resulted in a 4x decrease in simulation
time. I suspect the reason for this was because the overhead of
calling functions on small arrays outweighs the increase in speed
using Numpy's optimized C code. I was normalizing single vectors and
taking cross products between two vectors at a time many times during
each loop iteration.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;A brief glance at Python's multiprocessing module&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href="http://pymotw.com/2/multiprocessing/basics.html"&gt;PyMOTW&lt;/a&gt; has a good, minimal description of the main aspects of the
multiprocessing module. They state that the simplest way to create
tasks on different cores of a machine is to create new &lt;b&gt;Process&lt;/b&gt;
objects with target functions. Each object is then set to execute by
calling its &lt;b&gt;start()&lt;/b&gt; method.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The basic example from their site looks like this:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;import multiprocessing

def worker():
    """worker function"""
    print 'Worker'
    return

if __name__ == '__main__':
    jobs = []
    for i in range(5):
        p = multiprocessing.Process(target=worker)
        jobs.append(p)
        p.start()
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In this example, it's important to create the Process instances inside
the
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;if __name__ == '__main__':
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
section of the script because child processes import the script where
the target function is contained. Placing the object instantiation in
this section prevents an infinite, recursive string of such
instantiations. A workaround to this is to define the function in a
different script and import it into the namespace.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To send arguments to the function (&lt;b&gt;worker()&lt;/b&gt; in the example above),
we can use the &lt;b&gt;args&lt;/b&gt; keyword in the Process object instantiation like
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;p = multiprocessing.Process(target=worker, args=(i,))
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A very important thing to note is that the arguments must be objects
that can be pickled using Python's pickle module. If an argument is a
class instance, this means that every attritube of that class must be
pickleable.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
An important class in the multiprocessing module is a &lt;b&gt;Pool&lt;/b&gt;. A &lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3.4/library/multiprocessing.html#multiprocessing.pool.Pool"&gt;Pool&lt;/a&gt;
object controls a pool of worker processes. Jobs can be submitted to
the Pool, which then sends the jobs to the individual workers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The &lt;b&gt;Pool.map()&lt;/b&gt; achieves the same functionality as Matlab's &lt;b&gt;parfor&lt;/b&gt;
construct. This method essentially applies a function to each element
in an iterable and returns the results. For example, if I wanted to
square each number in a list of integers between 0 and 9 and perform
the square operation on multiple processors, I would write a function
for squaring an argument, and supply this function and the list of
integers to &lt;b&gt;Pool.map()&lt;/b&gt;. The code looks like this:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;import multiprocessing

def funSquare(num):
    return num ** 2

if __name__ == '__main__':
    pool = multiprocessing.Pool()
    results = pool.map(funSquare, range(10))
    print(results)
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-3" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-3"&gt;Design the solution to the problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In my parameter sweep, I have two classes: one is an object that I'm
simulating and the other acts as a controller that sends parameters to
the structure and collects the results of the simulation. Everything
was written in a serial fashion and I want to change it so the bulk of
the work is performed in parallel.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
After the bottlenecks were identified in the serial code, I began
thinking about how the the problem of parameter sweeps could be
addressed using the multiprocessing module.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The solution requirements I identified for my parameter sweep are as
follows:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accept two values (one for each parameter) from the range of values
to test as inputs to the simulation.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For each pair of values, run the simulation as an independent
process.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Return the results of the simulation as as a list or Numpy array.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I often choose to return the results as Numpy arrays since I can
easily pickle them when saving to a disk. This may change depending on
your specific problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-4" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-4"&gt;Implementation of the solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I'll now give a simplified example of how this solution to the
parameter sweep can be implemented using Python's multiprocessing
module. I won't use objects like in my real code, but will first
demonstrate an example where &lt;b&gt;Pool.map()&lt;/b&gt; is applied to a list of
numbers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;import multiprocessing

def runSimulation(params):
    """This is the main processing function. It will contain whatever
    code should be run on multiple processors.
    
    """
    param1, param2 = params
    # Example computation
    processedData = []
    for ctr in range(1000000):
        processedData.append(param1 * ctr - param2 ** 2)

    return processedData

if __name__ == '__main__':
    # Define the parameters to test
    param1 = range(100)
    param2 = range(2, 202, 2)

    # Zip the parameters because pool.map() takes only one iterable
    params = zip(param1, param2)
    
    pool = multiprocessing.Pool()
    results = pool.map(runSimulation, params)
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is a rather silly example of a simulation, but I think it
illustrates the point nicely. In the &lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="underline"&gt;&lt;span class="underline"&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt; portion of the code, I
first define two lists for each parameter value that I want to
'simulate.' These parameters are zipped together in this example
because &lt;b&gt;Pool.map()&lt;/b&gt; takes only one iterable as its argument. The pool
is opened using with &lt;b&gt;multiprocessing.Pool()&lt;/b&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Most of the work is performed in the function
&lt;b&gt;runSimulation(params)&lt;/b&gt;. It takes a tuple of two parameters which are
unpacked. Then, these parameters are used in the for loop to build a
list of simulated values which is eventually returned.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Returning to the &lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="underline"&gt;&lt;span class="underline"&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt; section, each simulation is run on a
different core of my machine using the &lt;b&gt;Pool.map()&lt;/b&gt; function. This
applies the function called &lt;b&gt;runSimulation()&lt;/b&gt; to the values in the
&lt;b&gt;params&lt;/b&gt; iterable. In other words, it calls the code described in
&lt;b&gt;runSimulation()&lt;/b&gt; with a different pair of values in params.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
All the results are eventually returned in a list in the same order as
the parameter iterable. This means that the first element in the
&lt;b&gt;results&lt;/b&gt; list corresponds to parameters of 0 and 2 in this example.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-5" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-5"&gt;Iterables over arbitrary objects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In my real simulation code, I use a class to encapsulate a number of
structural parameters and methods for simulating a polymer model. So
long as instances of this class can be &lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/pickle.html"&gt;pickled&lt;/a&gt;, I can use them as the
iterable in &lt;b&gt;Pool.map()&lt;/b&gt;, not just lists of floating point numbers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;import multiprocessing

class simObject():
    def __init__(self, params):
        self.param1, self.param2 = params

def runSimulation(objInstance):
    """This is the main processing function. It will contain whatever
    code should be run on multiple processors.
    
    """
    param1, param2 = objInstance.param1, objInstance.param2
    # Example computation
    processedData = []
    for ctr in range(1000000):
        processedData.append(param1 * ctr - param2 ** 2)

    return processedData

if __name__ == '__main__':
    # Define the parameters to test
    param1 = range(100)
    param2 = range(2, 202, 2)

    objList = []
    # Create a list of objects to feed into pool.map()
    for p1, p2 in zip(param1, param2):
        objList.append(simObject((p1, p2)))

    pool = multiprocessing.Pool()
    results = pool.map(runSimulation, objList)
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Again, this is a silly example, but it demonstrates that lists of
objects can be used in the parameter sweep, allowing for easy
parallelization of object-oriented code.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Instead of &lt;b&gt;runSimulation()&lt;/b&gt;, you may want to apply an instance method
to a list in &lt;b&gt;pool.map()&lt;/b&gt;. A naïve way to do this is to replace
&lt;b&gt;runSimulation&lt;/b&gt; with with the method name but this too causes
problems. I won't go into the details here, but one solution is to use
an instance's &lt;b&gt;__call__()&lt;/b&gt; method and pass the object instance into
the pool. More details can be found &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/1816958/cant-pickle-type-instancemethod-when-using-pythons-multiprocessing-pool-ma"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-6" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-6"&gt;Comparing computation times&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-6"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The following code makes a rough comparison between computation time
for the parallel and serial versions of &lt;b&gt;map()&lt;/b&gt;:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;import multiprocessing
import time

def runSimulation(params):
    """This is the main processing function. It will contain whatever
    code should be run on multiple processors.
    
    """
    param1, param2 = params
    # Example computation
    processedData = []
    for ctr in range(1000000):
        processedData.append(param1 * ctr - param2 ** 2)

    return processedData

if __name__ == '__main__':
    # Define the parameters to test
    param1 = range(100)
    param2 = range(2, 202, 2)

    params = zip(param1, param2)

    pool = multiprocessing.Pool()

    # Parallel map
    tic = time.time()
    results = pool.map(runSimulation, params)
    toc = time.time()

    # Serial map
    tic2 = time.time()
    results = map(runSimulation, params)
    toc2 = time.time()

    print('Parallel processing time: %r\nSerial processing time: %r'
          % (toc - tic, toc2 - tic2))
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
On my machine, &lt;b&gt;pool.map()&lt;/b&gt; ran in 9.6 seconds, but the serial version
took 163.3 seconds. My laptop has 8 cores, so I would have expected
the speedup to be a factor of 8, not a factor of 16. I'm not sure why
it's 16, but I suspect part of the reason is that measuring system
time using the &lt;b&gt;time.time()&lt;/b&gt; function is not wholly accurate.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-7" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-7"&gt;Important points&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-7"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I can verify that all the cores are being utilized on my machine while
the code is running by using the &lt;a href="http://hisham.hm/htop/"&gt;htop&lt;/a&gt; console program. In some cases,
Python modules like Numpy, scipy, etc. may limit processes in Python
to running on only one core on Linux machines, which defeats the
purpose of writing concurrent code in this case. (See for example &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/15639779/what-determines-whether-different-python-processes-are-assigned-to-the-same-or-d/15641148#15641148"&gt;this
discussion&lt;/a&gt;.) To fix this, we can import Python's &lt;b&gt;os&lt;/b&gt; module to reset
the task affinity in our code:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;os.system("taskset -p 0xff %d" % os.getpid())
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-8" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-8"&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-8"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think that Matlab's &lt;b&gt;parfor&lt;/b&gt; construct is easier to use because one
doesn't have to consider the nuances of writing concurrent code. So
long as each loop iteration is independent of the others, you simply
write a &lt;b&gt;parfor&lt;/b&gt; instead of &lt;b&gt;for&lt;/b&gt; and you're set.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In Python, you have to prevent infinite, recursive function calls by
placing your code in the &lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="underline"&gt;&lt;span class="underline"&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt; section of your script or by
placing the function in a different script and importing it. You also
have to be sure that Numpy and other Python modules that use BLAS
haven't reset the core affinity. What you gain over Matlab's
implementation is the power of using Python as a general programming
language with a lot of tools for scientific computing. This and the
multiprocessing module is free; you have to have an institute license
or pay for Matlab's &lt;a href="http://www.mathworks.com/products/parallel-computing/"&gt;Parallel Computing Toolbox&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>computing</category><category>python</category><guid>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/learning-pythons-multiprocessing-module.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2014 17:42:23 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>