<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Kyle M. Douglass (Posts about devops)</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/categories/devops.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2019 08:09:28 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Create a custom Raspbian image with pi-gen: part 2</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/create-a-custom-raspbian-image-with-pi-gen-part-2/</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/create-a-custom-raspbian-image-with-pi-gen-part-1/"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I discussed how to setup user accounts and
locales in a custom Raspbian image using pi-gen. In this follow-up
post, I will discuss the main problems that I want to solve:
automatically configuring the wireless network and ssh on a new
Raspberry Pi without a terminal attached directly to the Pi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="set-up-the-wireless-network"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Set up the wireless network&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-wpa-supplicant"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The WPA supplicant&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Pi's wireless credentials are configured in stage 2 in the file
&lt;strong&gt;stage2/02-net-tweaks/files/wpa_supplicant.conf&lt;/strong&gt;. Here's how it
looks by default:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
ctrl_interface=DIR=/var/run/wpa_supplicant GROUP=netdev
update_config=1
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the blogs &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://learnthinksolvecreate.wordpress.com/2017/07/25/pi-gen-setting-default-wifi-settings/"&gt;Learn Think Solve Create&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.raspberrypi-spy.co.uk/2017/04/manually-setting-up-pi-wifi-using-wpa_supplicant-conf/"&gt;Raspberry
Spy&lt;/a&gt;, the first thing we should do is add our country code to the top
of this file with the line &lt;cite&gt;country=CH&lt;/cite&gt;. (Use your own country code
for this.) Next, we want to enter the details for our wireless
network, which includes its name and the password. For security
reasons that I hope are obvious, we should not store the password in
this file. Instead, we create a hash of the password and put that
inside the file. The command to create the password hash is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code shell"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_89a8d4ccb392450a8c4277b923f54354-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;wpa_passphrase ESSID PASSWORD &amp;gt; psk
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;where ESSID is our wireless network's name. Note that I also used a
space before the &lt;code class="shell"&gt;wpa_passphrase&lt;/code&gt; command to prevent the
password being written to my .bash_history file. Now, we copy and
paste the contents of the file &lt;strong&gt;psk&lt;/strong&gt; into the wpa_supplicant.conf
and remove the comment that contains the actual password:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
country=CH
ctrl_interface=DIR=/var/run/wpa_supplicant GROUP=netdev
update_config=1
network={
        ssid=YOUR_ESSID_HERE
        psk=YOUR_PSK_HASH_HERE
}
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="configure-the-wireless-network-interfaces"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Configure the wireless network interfaces&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After having configured the supplicant, we next move on to configuring
the network interfaces used by Raspbian. The appropriate file is found
in &lt;strong&gt;stage1/02-net-tweaks/files/interfaces&lt;/strong&gt;. In my post &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/connecting-a-raspberry-pi-to-a-home-linux-network/"&gt;Connecting a
Raspberry Pi to a Home Linux Network&lt;/a&gt; I described how to set up the
network interfaces by editing &lt;strong&gt;/etc/network/interfaces&lt;/strong&gt;. Much of the
information presented in that post has now been superseded in Raspbian
by the DHCP daemon. For now, we will use the interfaces file to
instruct our Pi to use DHCP and will use &lt;strong&gt;/etc/dhcpcd.conf&lt;/strong&gt; at a
later time to set up a static IP address when provisioning the Pi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We first need to make a few changes to make the interfaces file aware
of the credentials in the wpa supplicant configuration file. According
to the blog &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://kerneldriver.wordpress.com/2012/10/21/configuring-wpa2-using-wpa_supplicant-on-the-raspberry-pi/"&gt;kerneldriver&lt;/a&gt;, we need modify the
/etc/networe/interfaces file as such:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
auto lo

iface lo inet loopback
iface eth0 inet dhcp

auto wlan0
iface wlan0 inet manual
     wpa-roam /etc/wpa_supplicant/wpa_supplicant.conf
iface default inet dhcp
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first modification, I specify that I want the wirless interface
&lt;strong&gt;wlan0&lt;/strong&gt; started automatically with &lt;cite&gt;auto wlan0&lt;/cite&gt;. Next, I specify
that the wlan0 interface should use the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://manpages.debian.org/stretch/ifupdown/interfaces.5.en.html#The_manual_Method"&gt;manual inet address family&lt;/a&gt;
with the line &lt;cite&gt;iface wlan0 inet manual&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the man pages, "[the manual] method may be used to define
interfaces for which no configuration is done by default." After this
we use the &lt;cite&gt;wpa-roam&lt;/cite&gt; command to specify the location of the
wpa_supplicant.conf file that we previously modified. The wireless
ESSID and password are therefore not defined in interfaces, but rather
reference them inside wpa_supplicant.conf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you noticed that wpa-roam doesn't appear as an option in
documentation on the interfaces file and were wondering why, it's
because other programs like wpasupplicant may provide additional
options to the interfaces file. A similar command is &lt;cite&gt;wpa-conf&lt;/cite&gt;, but I
do not quite yet understand the difference between these two commands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the wpa-roam command, we configure the default options for
all networks in our wpa_supplicant.conf file with the line &lt;cite&gt;iface
default inet dhcp&lt;/cite&gt;. At this point, we save the setup of the static IP
address for a later time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more information, see &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://manpages.debian.org/stretch/ifupdown/interfaces.5.en.html"&gt;the interfaces man page for Debian
Stretch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="change-the-hostname"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Change the hostname&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our Pi's hostname may be changed from the default (raspberrypi) by
modifying the line in &lt;strong&gt;stage1/02-net-tweaks/files/hostname&lt;/strong&gt;. See
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc1178"&gt;RFC 1178&lt;/a&gt; for tips on choosing a hostname.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to modifying the hostname file, we need to update
&lt;strong&gt;stage1/02-net-tweaks/00-patches/01-hosts.diff&lt;/strong&gt; and change
raspberrypi to the new hostname:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
Index: jessie-stage1/rootfs/etc/hosts
===================================================================
--- jessie-stage1.orig/rootfs/etc/hosts
+++ jessie-stage1/rootfs/etc/hosts
@@ -3,3 +3,4 @@
 ff02::1                ip6-allnodes
 ff02::2                ip6-allrouters

+127.0.1.1      NEW_HOSTNAME_HERE
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="set-the-dns-servers"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Set the DNS servers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DNS servers are configured in
&lt;strong&gt;export-image/02-network/files/resolv.conf&lt;/strong&gt;. By default, mine was
already configured to use one of Google's DNS servers (8.8.8.8). I
added a secondary Google DNS address as well:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
nameserver 8.8.8.8
nameserver 8.8.4.4
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="enable-ssh"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Enable SSH&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enabling SSH is simple. Open &lt;strong&gt;stage2/01-sys-tweaks/01-run.sh&lt;/strong&gt; and
change the line &lt;code class="shell"&gt;systemctl disable ssh&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code class="shell"&gt;systemctl
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;enable&lt;/span&gt; ssh&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I later learned that we can also enable ssh on a headless pi by
adding an empty file named &lt;strong&gt;ssh&lt;/strong&gt; to the boot partition of a standard
Raspbian image. See here for more details:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/documentation/remote-access/ssh/"&gt;https://www.raspberrypi.org/documentation/remote-access/ssh/&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="configuring-ssh-keys-or-not"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Configuring SSH keys (or not)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided after writing much of this tutorial that pi-gen was not
necessarily the best tool for adding my public SSH keys. So long as I
have network access and SSH enabled, I can easily add my keys using
&lt;code class="shell"&gt;ssh-copy-id&lt;/code&gt;. Furthermore, after following this tutorial,
there still remains a lot of setup and customization steps. These can
more easily be performed manually or by server automation tools like
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.fabfile.org/"&gt;Fabric&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.ansible.com/"&gt;Ansible&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I think that at this point we can stop with our
customization of the image with pi-gen and move to a different
tool. We have a basic Raspbian image that is already configured for
our home network and that serves as a starting point for more complete
customization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="conclusion"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tutorial and my &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/create-a-custom-raspbian-image-with-pi-gen-part-1/"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; demonstrated how to create a
custom Raspbian image that is pre-configured for&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;our home wireless network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;our locale information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ssh&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, we can do much, much more with pi-gen, but other tools
exist for the purpose of configuring a server. These tutorials at
least allow you to setup a new Raspberry Pi without having to manually
configure its most basic functionality. Happy Pi'ing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>devops</category><category>raspberry pi</category><category>raspbian</category><guid>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/create-a-custom-raspbian-image-with-pi-gen-part-2/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jul 2018 16:25:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Create a custom Raspbian image with pi-gen: part 1</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/create-a-custom-raspbian-image-with-pi-gen-part-1/</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Docker has been an amazing tool for improving my development
efficiency on the Raspberry Pi. For example, I recently used it to
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/how-i-built-a-cross-compilation-workflow-for-the-raspberry-pi/"&gt;cross-compile a large C++ and Python library&lt;/a&gt; for the Pi's ARM
architecture on my x86_64 laptop. However, in that post I took it for
granted that I had already set up my Raspberry Pi with user accounts,
packages, ssh keys, etc. Performing these steps manually on a fresh
install of the Pi's &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/downloads/raspbian/"&gt;Raspbian&lt;/a&gt; operating system can become tedious,
especially because ssh needs to be manually enabled before doing any
remote work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, the Raspberry Pi developers have provided us with
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/RPi-Distro/pi-gen"&gt;pi-gen&lt;/a&gt;, a useful collection of Shell scripts and a Docker container
for creating custom Raspbian images. In this post, I will summarize
the steps that I take in using pi-gen to create my own, personalized
Raspbian image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;After I wrote this post, I found a set of posts at&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://learnthinksolvecreate.wordpress.com/category/raspberry-pi/pi-gen/"&gt;Learn Think
Solve Create&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;that describe many of the tasks I explain here. Be
sure to check them out for another take on modifying Raspbian images.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="clone-the-pi-gen-repository"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Clone the pi-gen repository&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is as easy as cloning the git repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code shell"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_db419c32ee174b79bcf51fa6499e641c-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;git clone git@github.com:RPi-Distro/pi-gen.git
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, you can use the https address instead of ssh, which is
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/RPi-Distro/pi-gen.git"&gt;https://github.com/RPi-Distro/pi-gen.git&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From now on, all directories in this post will be relative to the root
pi-gen directory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="build-the-official-raspbian-images"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Build the official Raspbian images&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By default, the pi-gen repository will build the official Raspbian
images. Doing this once before making any modifications is probably a
good idea; if you can't build the official images, how will you be
able to build a custom image?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two main scripts that you can use to do this: &lt;strong&gt;build.sh&lt;/strong&gt;
and &lt;strong&gt;build-docker.sh&lt;/strong&gt;. build.sh requires you to install the packages
that are listed in the repository's README.md file, whereas
build-docker.sh requires only that you have Docker already installed
on your computer. I'm going to be using the Docker-based build script
for the rest of this post. If you don't have Docker installed on your
system, you can &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://docs.docker.com/install/"&gt;follow the instructions here&lt;/a&gt; for the community
edition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="name-your-image"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Name your image&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First we need to give a name to our image, even if we use the default
build. To do this, we assign a name to a variable called &lt;strong&gt;IMG_NAME&lt;/strong&gt;
inside a file called &lt;strong&gt;config&lt;/strong&gt; that is located inside the root pi-gen
folder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code shell"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_cac3bac8a65b4d589474934b67cbd8d0-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"IMG_NAME=my_name"&lt;/span&gt; &amp;gt; config
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="build-the-default-image"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Build the default image&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we've named our image, we can go ahead and run the build script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code shell"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_44c57045177a40a0bc8a08b56f00bd61-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;./build-docker.sh
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Be prepared to wait a while when running this script; the full build
took well over half an hour on my laptop and with the Docker volume
located on a SSD. It also consumed several GB of space on the SSD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="resuming-a-failed-build"&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Resuming a failed build&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first time I used pi-gen the build failed twice. Once, it hung
without doing anything for several minutes, so I canceled it with a
&lt;strong&gt;Ctrl-C&lt;/strong&gt; command. The other time I encountered a hash error when
installing a Debian package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can resume a failed build from the point of failure by assigning
the value 1 to the CONTINUE variable when calling build-docker.sh
again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code shell"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_fd6fe9df7b224f48b1736e341ae377dc-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;CONTINUE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; ./build-docker.sh
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;If we don't want to run previously built stages, we can simply place a
file inside the corresponding folder named SKIP. For example, if our
build fails at stage2, we can place SKIP files inside the stage0 and
stage1 folders, then rerun the build-docker.sh script with
CONTINUE=1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I have sometimes noticed that I have to also rebuild
the stage &lt;em&gt;prior&lt;/em&gt; to the one where the build failed. In the worst
case, I had to rebuild all the stages because the fixes I applied to a
file in stage2 were not accounted for when I tried to skip building
stages 0 and 1. YMMV with this; I have no idea how well the SKIP
mechanism works for the normal build.sh script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a successful build, we can find our custom images located inside
the &lt;strong&gt;deploy&lt;/strong&gt; folder of the pi-gen directory. These may then be
written onto a SD card and used as a standard Raspbian image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can ensure that the build container is preserved even after successful
builds using&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code shell"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_e379a9311cf54c33806ff733d2694d97-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;PRESERVE_CONTAINER&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; ./build-docker.sh
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="custom-raspbian-images"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Custom Raspbian images&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we've got the default build working, let's start by
customizing the build process. For this post, I have the following
goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build only the &lt;em&gt;lite&lt;/em&gt; version of the Raspbian images&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add a custom user account and delete the default &lt;em&gt;pi&lt;/em&gt; account&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set the Pi's locale information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a follow-up post, I will discuss the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setup the WiFi for a home network&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setup ssh so that we can log on to the Pi remotely on its first
startup&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="building-just-raspbian-lite"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Building just Raspbian Lite&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Raspbian Lite is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://raspberrypi.stackexchange.com/questions/39932/differences-between-raspbian-jessie-and-raspbian-jessie-lite#39933"&gt;minimal Raspbian image&lt;/a&gt; without the X windows
server and speciality modules that would otherwise make Raspbian more
user friendly. It's an ideal starting point for projects that are
highly specialized, require only a few packages, and do not require a
GUI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;pi-gen creates Raspbian images in sequential steps called stages. At
the time of this writing, there were five stages, with stages 2, 4,
and 5 producing images of the operating system. Building everything
from stage 0 up to and including stage 2 produces a Raspbian Lite
image. We can speed up the build process and save harddrive space by
disabling all the later stages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To disable the build for a particular a stage, we add an empty file
called &lt;strong&gt;SKIP&lt;/strong&gt; inside the corresponding stage folder of the pi-gen
root directory, just as we did above when skipping previously built
stages. We also disable the explicit creation of images by adding an
empty file called &lt;strong&gt;SKIP_IMAGES&lt;/strong&gt; to stages 4 and 5. (We don't need to
add a SKIP_IMAGES file to the stage3 folder because no image is
produced at this stage.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code shell"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_990994ad730949059c3ae65fd240c93d-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;touch ./stage3/SKIP ./stage4/SKIP ./stage5/SKIP
&lt;a name="rest_code_990994ad730949059c3ae65fd240c93d-2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;touch ./stage4/SKIP_IMAGES ./stage5/SKIP_IMAGES
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, when we run build-docker.sh, pi-gen will only build and produce
one image for Raspbian Lite in the deploy directory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="add-a-custom-user-account"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Add a custom user account&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The default user in Raspbian is called &lt;strong&gt;pi&lt;/strong&gt;. This account is created
in stage1 in the the script &lt;strong&gt;stage1/01-sys-tweaks/00-run.sh&lt;/strong&gt;. This
account is not very secure because it and its password, &lt;em&gt;raspberry&lt;/em&gt;,
are the well-known defaults in Raspbian. Let's go ahead and change
them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The relevant lines in the script look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code shell"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_f342c92a6d6c4693ad1676a0ec27cfc1-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;on_chroot &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt; EOF&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_f342c92a6d6c4693ad1676a0ec27cfc1-2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;if ! id -u pi &amp;gt;/dev/null 2&amp;gt;&amp;amp;1; then&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_f342c92a6d6c4693ad1676a0ec27cfc1-3"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;     adduser --disabled-password --gecos "" pi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_f342c92a6d6c4693ad1676a0ec27cfc1-4"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;fi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_f342c92a6d6c4693ad1676a0ec27cfc1-5"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;echo "pi:raspberry" | chpasswd&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_f342c92a6d6c4693ad1676a0ec27cfc1-6"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;echo "root:root" | chpasswd&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_f342c92a6d6c4693ad1676a0ec27cfc1-7"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;EOF&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;The user pi is created with the line
&lt;code class="shell"&gt;adduser --disabled-password --gecos &lt;span class="s2"&gt;""&lt;/span&gt; pi&lt;/code&gt; if it doesn't
already exist. According to the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://manpages.ubuntu.com/manpages/trusty/man8/adduser.8.html"&gt;adduser man pages&lt;/a&gt;
The --disabled-password flag prevents the program passwd from setting
the account's password when adduser is run, but remote logins without
password authentication to the pi account are still allowed. the
&lt;code class="shell"&gt;--gecos &lt;span class="s2"&gt;""&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt; flag simply adds an empty string to the
/etc/passwd file for the pi account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the user is created, &lt;em&gt;raspberry&lt;/em&gt; is set as pi's password and
&lt;em&gt;root&lt;/em&gt; is set as the root password in the lines &lt;code class="shell"&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="s2"&gt;"pi:raspberry"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; chpasswd&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class="shell"&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"root:root"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; chpasswd&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's start by modifying the pi account. For the sake of this example,
let's change its name to alphapi. For the password, we will generate a
&lt;strong&gt;temporary, random&lt;/strong&gt; password and write it to a file in the deploy
directory. We'll do the same for root. The modifications look like the
following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code shell"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_fbc787ef08fb44148b681cb15056f252-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;user_passwd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt; /dev/urandom tr -dc _A-Z-a-z-0-9 &lt;span class="p"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; head -c&lt;span class="si"&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;:-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_fbc787ef08fb44148b681cb15056f252-2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;root_passwd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt; /dev/urandom tr -dc _A-Z-a-z-0-9 &lt;span class="p"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; head -c&lt;span class="si"&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;:-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_fbc787ef08fb44148b681cb15056f252-3"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_fbc787ef08fb44148b681cb15056f252-4"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Write passwords to a file.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_fbc787ef08fb44148b681cb15056f252-5"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;cat &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;EOF &amp;gt; /pi-gen/deploy/users&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_fbc787ef08fb44148b681cb15056f252-6"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;${user_passwd}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_fbc787ef08fb44148b681cb15056f252-7"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;${root_passwd}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_fbc787ef08fb44148b681cb15056f252-8"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;EOF&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_fbc787ef08fb44148b681cb15056f252-9"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_fbc787ef08fb44148b681cb15056f252-10"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;on_chroot &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt; EOF&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_fbc787ef08fb44148b681cb15056f252-11"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;if ! id -u alphapi &amp;gt;/dev/null 2&amp;gt;&amp;amp;1; then&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_fbc787ef08fb44148b681cb15056f252-12"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;     adduser --disabled-password --gecos "" alphapi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_fbc787ef08fb44148b681cb15056f252-13"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;fi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_fbc787ef08fb44148b681cb15056f252-14"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;echo "alphapi:${user_passwd}" | chpasswd&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_fbc787ef08fb44148b681cb15056f252-15"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;echo "root:${root_passwd}" | chpasswd&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_fbc787ef08fb44148b681cb15056f252-16"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;EOF&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first two lines create random alphanumeric passwords for the users
alphapi and root. They should be changed immediately when the image is
first run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code shell"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_4e749f4c258b4dc5afda8e0a906eb803-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;user_passwd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt; /dev/urandom tr -dc _A-Z-a-z-0-9 &lt;span class="p"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; head -c&lt;span class="si"&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;:-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_4e749f4c258b4dc5afda8e0a906eb803-2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;root_passwd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt; /dev/urandom tr -dc _A-Z-a-z-0-9 &lt;span class="p"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; head -c&lt;span class="si"&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;:-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;This way of password generation works by reading random bytes from
/dev/urandom and redirecting them to the standard input of the tr
command, which filters the input so only alphanumeric characters
remain. Next, the output is piped to the head command, which outputs
only the first eight alphanumeric characters produced in this fashion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The passwords are then written to a file named &lt;strong&gt;users&lt;/strong&gt; inside the
deploy directory where the outputs will eventually be placed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code shell"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_bba80531265646e4bda4259e7755a514-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Write passwords to a file.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_bba80531265646e4bda4259e7755a514-2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;cat &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;EOF &amp;gt; /pi-gen/deploy/users&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_bba80531265646e4bda4259e7755a514-3"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;${user_passwd}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_bba80531265646e4bda4259e7755a514-4"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;${root_passwd}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_bba80531265646e4bda4259e7755a514-5"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;EOF&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;The remaining parts of the script are more-or-less the same as before,
except I changed pi to alphapi and used variable substitution for the
passwords.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running ./build-docker.sh at this point will raise an error in stage02
because it's at this stage where the user pi is added to the various
groups on the system. We therefore need to open
&lt;strong&gt;stage2/01-sys-tweaks/01-run.sh&lt;/strong&gt; and modify the following lines,
replacing pi with alphapi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code shell"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_7d3b5f0a9ce949949be9de68b5a6e323-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; GRP in adm dialout cdrom audio users sudo video games plugdev input gpio spi i2c netdev&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;do&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_7d3b5f0a9ce949949be9de68b5a6e323-2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;    adduser alphapi &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$GRP&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_7d3b5f0a9ce949949be9de68b5a6e323-3"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;done&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="set-the-locale-information"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Set the locale information&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The locale information used by your operating system may be modified
as follows. Open &lt;strong&gt;stage0/01-locale/00-debconf&lt;/strong&gt;. I personally changed
every occurence of en_GB.UTF-8 to en_US.UTF-8, but you can set your
locale accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code shell"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_be5df10afbc9427ca4da70e476c69892-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Locales to be generated:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_be5df10afbc9427ca4da70e476c69892-2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Choices: All locales, aa_DJ ISO-8859-1, aa_DJ.UTF-8 UTF-8, ...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_be5df10afbc9427ca4da70e476c69892-3"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;locales locales/locales_to_be_generated multiselect en_US.UTF-8 UTF-8
&lt;a name="rest_code_be5df10afbc9427ca4da70e476c69892-4"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Default locale for the system environment:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_be5df10afbc9427ca4da70e476c69892-5"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Choices: None, C.UTF-8, en_US.UTF-8&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name="rest_code_be5df10afbc9427ca4da70e476c69892-6"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;locales locales/default_environment_locale   &lt;span class="k"&gt;select&lt;/span&gt;  en_US.UTF-8
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Next, we open &lt;strong&gt;stage2/01-sys-tweaks/00-debconf&lt;/strong&gt;. I currently live in
Europe, so I made the following changes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
tzdata        tzdata/Areas    select  Europe
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also made the following changes to switch from the default British
English to American English:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code shell"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_c015bf5c41cb4d11808ed86bad8bfee5-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;keyboard-configuration keyboard-configuration/xkb-keymap &lt;span class="k"&gt;select&lt;/span&gt; us
&lt;a name="rest_code_c015bf5c41cb4d11808ed86bad8bfee5-2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;keyboard-configuration keyboard-configuration/fvariant  &lt;span class="k"&gt;select&lt;/span&gt;  English &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;US&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; - English &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;US&lt;span class="se"&gt;\,&lt;/span&gt; international with dead keys&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note that the comment in 00-debconf above the
keyboard-configuration/xkb-keymap line erroneously states that
American English is an option, but it's not. You need to change it
from "gb" to "us" if you want the American layout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="using-the-custom-image"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Using the custom image&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all these changes, we can build our new image by running
&lt;code class="shell"&gt;./build-docker.sh&lt;/code&gt; and, if successful, find a .zip file inside
the deploy directory with the image name and date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To use this image, we unzip the file to extract the .img file inside
it. Next, we need to copy it onto a SD card that will plug into the
pi. I have a SD card reader/writer on my laptop for which I check for
its Linux device name by running &lt;code class="shell"&gt;lsblk&lt;/code&gt; before and after
plugging in the card. (The device that appears in the output of lsblk
after plugging it in is its name, which is &lt;strong&gt;/dev/mmcblk0&lt;/strong&gt; on my
laptop). Once I get its device name, I use the Linux &lt;code class="shell"&gt;dd&lt;/code&gt;
command to copy the contents of the image onto the card. (Be sure to
change /dev/mccblk0 to match the name that your system gives to your
SD card device.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code shell"&gt;&lt;a name="rest_code_f7693cac2fa34488bc491db627f3c064-1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;sudo dd &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="m"&gt;2018&lt;/span&gt;-07-21-my_name-lite.img &lt;span class="nv"&gt;of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;/dev/mmcblk0 &lt;span class="nv"&gt;bs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="m"&gt;4096&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; sync
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please be EXTREMELY careful that you get the device name right.&lt;/strong&gt;
It's not very difficult to write the contents of the image file over
your root partition or other important data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After writing the image, we can plug the SD card into our pi, boot it
up, and try logging in as alphapi with the random password that was
created in the users file. &lt;strong&gt;Be sure at this point to change your
user's and root's password&lt;/strong&gt;. We can also verify that the keyboard was
set to US English by typing Shift-3 and observing whether we get a
hashtag (#) symbol and not the symbol for the British pound currency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a follow-up post, I will describe how to setup the network and SSH
so I can continue to setup my Raspberry Pi without ever needing a
terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>devops</category><category>raspberry pi</category><category>raspbian</category><guid>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/create-a-custom-raspbian-image-with-pi-gen-part-1/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 21 Jul 2018 10:31:28 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>