<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Kyle M. Douglass (optics)</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/categories/optics.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2016 09:19:44 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Beware the paraxial approximation in microscopy</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/beware-the-paraxial-approximation-in-microscopy.html</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I have had a difficult time resolving what originally seemed to be an
inconsistency between a 2004 research article about estimating
microscope pupil functions and the body of knowledge concerning the
theory of aberrations in optical systems.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the article by Hanser, et al.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" name="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/beware-the-paraxial-approximation-in-microscopy.html#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, the authors utilize an imaging model
for calculating the amplitude point-spread function of an optical
system that incorporates defocus as an exponential term inside the
Fourier transform integral:
&lt;/p&gt;

\begin{equation*}
\text{PSF}_{\text{A}} \left( x, y, z \right) = \iint_{pupil} P \left( k_x, k_y \right) e^{i k_z z} e^{i \left( k_{x}x + k_{y}y \right)} dk_x dk_y
\end{equation*}

&lt;p&gt;
where \(k_z = \sqrt{\left( 2 \pi n / \lambda \right)^2 - \left( k_x^2 +
k_y^2 \right)}\). (I changed the notation of some variables used in the
text because the authors confusingly use \(k\) to represent spatial
frequency in units of &lt;i&gt;cycles per distance&lt;/i&gt; instead of the much more
common &lt;i&gt;radians per distance&lt;/i&gt;.) In the image plane at \(z = 0\), there
is no defocus and we get the amplitude point spread function (PSF) as
the Fourier transform of the pupil function \(P \left( k_x, k_y
\right)\) just like we would expect (see Goodman&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.2" name="fnr.2" class="footref" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/beware-the-paraxial-approximation-in-microscopy.html#fn.2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, Chapter 6,
pp. 129-131).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The problem arises when I try to verify this model when \(z\) is not
equal to zero by computing the defocused PSF using the wavefront error
for defocus. From the scalar diffraction theory of aberrations, the
defocused PSF is the Fourier transform of the pupil function
multiplied by a phase factor whose phase angle is proportional to the
wavefront error \(W \left( k_x, k_y \right)\)
&lt;/p&gt;

\begin{equation*}
\text{PSF}_{\text{A}} \left( x, y, z \right) = \iint_{pupil} P \left( k_x, k_y \right) e^{i k W \left( k_x, k_y \right)} e^{i \left( k_{x}x + k_{y}y \right)} dk_x dk_y
\end{equation*}

&lt;p&gt;
Any textbook discussing Seidel aberrations will tell you that the
defocused wavefront error \(W\) is quadratic in the pupil plane
coordinates, i.e. \(W \sim k_x^2 + k_y^2\). Goodman even states this
with little justification later in Chapter 6 on p. 149 when discussing
defocus &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.2.100" name="fnr.2.100" class="footref" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/beware-the-paraxial-approximation-in-microscopy.html#fn.2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. So how can I reconcile the first equation in which the
defocus goes as the square root of a constant minus the squared pupil
coordinates with the second equation that is quadratic in pupil
coordinates?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The answer, as you might have guessed from the title of this post, is
that &lt;i&gt;the Seidel polynomial term for defocus is a result of applying
the paraxial approximation when computing the wavefront error&lt;/i&gt;. You
can see this by calculating the phase of a spherical wave in the pupil
plane that is centered on the axis in the image plane; Goodman states
it is quadratic without justification, but this is only true near the
axis. Mahajan offers a geometrical interpretation of \(W\) on p. 148,
where he notes that the path length difference for defocus "is
approximately equal to the difference of &lt;a href="http://liutaiomottola.com/formulae/sag.htm"&gt;sags&lt;/a&gt; of the reference sphere
and the wavefront.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.3" name="fnr.3" class="footref" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/beware-the-paraxial-approximation-in-microscopy.html#fn.3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;" He then goes on to derive the same expression
for \(W\) that Goodman gets; he states the approximation that he uses,
whereas Goodman implicitly assumes a quadratic phase front in the
pupil. Hanser et al., on the other hand, are essentially propagating
the plane wave angular spectrum from the image plane to nearby planes
to model defocus. I think that this should be rigorously correct since
no approximation is applied. For me, it is unfortunate that this was
not made clear in their paper because I spent quite a bit of time
trying to reconcile the two results.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The lesson of this story is to be sure you know about the
approximations that go into a "standard" result found in textbooks. I
falsely assumed that the Seidel aberrations were exact and that
Hanser, et al. were suspect when in fact it was the other way
around. Because the paraxial approximation is so widespread in optics
theory, it can often lie hidden behind an equation and its effects can
easily be taken for granted. This is a problem for the large NA
systems used in microscopy where the results of the paraxial
approximation are not often valid.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" name="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/beware-the-paraxial-approximation-in-microscopy.html#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p class="footpara"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.0022-2720.2004.01393.x/abstract;jsessionid=946CF30FA7FA65F1DB4C638D0C4DF00F.f02t04"&gt;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.0022-2720.2004.01393.x/abstract;jsessionid=946CF30FA7FA65F1DB4C638D0C4DF00F.f02t04&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.2" name="fn.2" class="footnum" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/beware-the-paraxial-approximation-in-microscopy.html#fnr.2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p class="footpara"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://books.google.ch/books/about/Introduction_to_Fourier_optics.html?id=ow5xs_Rtt9AC&amp;amp;redir_esc=y"&gt;https://books.google.ch/books/about/Introduction_to_Fourier_optics.html?id=ow5xs_Rtt9AC&amp;amp;redir_esc=y&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.3" name="fn.3" class="footnum" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/beware-the-paraxial-approximation-in-microscopy.html#fnr.3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p class="footpara"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://books.google.ch/books/about/Optical_Imaging_and_Aberrations_Ray_geom.html?id=I_1AAQAAIAAJ&amp;amp;redir_esc=y"&gt;https://books.google.ch/books/about/Optical_Imaging_and_Aberrations_Ray_geom.html?id=I_1AAQAAIAAJ&amp;amp;redir_esc=y&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>microscopy</category><category>optics</category><guid>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/beware-the-paraxial-approximation-in-microscopy.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2015 17:40:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What's the difference between a back focal plane and pupil plane?</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/whats-the-difference-between-a-back-focal-plane-and-pupil-plane.html</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Yesterday in the lab I asked one of my colleagues whether she knew
what the pupil plane of a microscope objective was. Her answer was
no. I then unknowingly proceeded to give her a description which I now
realize was false. I said that the pupil plane is the plane near the
backside of the objective where the light intensity is proportional to
the Fourier transform of the image. Later that evening, I realized
that this explanation was, in fact, wrong. I had described to her what
is the &lt;i&gt;back focal plane&lt;/i&gt; for an infinity-corrected objective.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Don't worry, I will correct myself when I see her later
today. However, this experience does raise one important question that
I have never seriously considered in optics: what is the meaningful
difference between the pupil plane of an optical system and its back
focal plane?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First, I should point out that there is no difference between a &lt;i&gt;back&lt;/i&gt;
focal plane and one of the two focal planes of an objective; these are
merely semantics that reflect the fact that we think of the sample as
being in front of the objective. The back focal plane is therefore the
focal plane of the objective located on the side opposite the
sample. Now, everyone who has taken a Fourier optics class has
probably learned the following mantra:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align="center"&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;The focal plane of a lens contains the Fourier transform of the
object.&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, this statement is usually what we remember, but in fact it
should look more like this:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align="center"&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;The focal plane of a lens contains the Fourier transform of the
object, except for every other detail we ignore in the math.&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
While it's true that the light intensity here reflects the sample's
two-dimensional Fourier transform, the general case often contains
additional phase factors and expressions to account for the pupil size
and apodization (see &lt;a href="https://books.google.ch/books?id=ow5xs_Rtt9AC&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;amp;dq=goodman+fourier+optics&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=0CB0Q6AEwAGoVChMI-5vjt5jGxwIVCMUUCh37ogzP#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=goodman%20fourier%20optics&amp;amp;f=false"&gt;Goodman&lt;/a&gt;, section 5.2). Regardless, it is in the
back focal plane where the light intensity contains information on the
angular spectrum that makes up the object.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In contrast, the pupil plane contains either the image of the
objective's aperture stop or the physical stop itself, depending on
what sets the limit on the numerical aperture of the objective in the
infinity space (again, see &lt;a href="https://books.google.ch/books?id=ow5xs_Rtt9AC&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;amp;dq=goodman+fourier+optics&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=0CB0Q6AEwAGoVChMI-5vjt5jGxwIVCMUUCh37ogzP#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=goodman%20fourier%20optics&amp;amp;f=false"&gt;Goodman&lt;/a&gt;, appendix B). Moreover, the pupil
plane is also used as the reference plane for quantifying the
objective's aberrations. This is because, for a diffraction-limited
system, the wavefront in the (exit) pupil plane will be a spherical
wave converging towards the image of a point source and truncated by
the aperture stop (&lt;a href="https://books.google.ch/books?id=ow5xs_Rtt9AC&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;amp;dq=goodman+fourier+optics&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=0CB0Q6AEwAGoVChMI-5vjt5jGxwIVCMUUCh37ogzP#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=goodman%20fourier%20optics&amp;amp;f=false"&gt;Goodman&lt;/a&gt; again discusses this in section
6.1). Deviations from the spherical reference wave serve as the means
to quantify the aberrations in a system.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
From an experimental point of view, the back focal plane is
interesting because it is used in Fourier microscopy, for which many
setups have been devised to image it (see Figure 1 in &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1507.04037"&gt;this excellent
arXiv submission&lt;/a&gt;.) What I really am wondering now is how one would go
about imaging the pupil plane as a means of exploring an objective's
aberrations, and whether this is at all feasible.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>optics</category><guid>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/whats-the-difference-between-a-back-focal-plane-and-pupil-plane.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 Aug 2015 06:49:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Paraxial Optics (2): What problem does it solve?</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paraxial optics is a tool to aid in building optical systems.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paraxial optics solves the imaging problem.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The imaging problem concerns finding the location, size, and
orientation of an image given an object and an optical system.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An optical system is a collection of objects like lenses, mirrors,
prisms, cameras, etc. that collects the light emitted or scattered
by an object and delivers it to another location where it can be
detected and processed for information.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The rules of paraxial optics allow for a perfect imaging system,
i.e. a system that creates a one-to-one correspondance between
points in an object plane and an image plane.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;Paraxial optics solves the imaging problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;In this post I will use paraxial optics to mean paraxial geometrical
optics. This is important since the paraxial approximation can also&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;i&gt;apply to the wave theory of light.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When learning a new theory, I often find it most useful to first
identify the problem that the theory was developed to solve. This
approach is particularly pertinent for learning paraxial optics, since
the theory is largely used as a tool to aid in the construction of
optical systems. Unfortunately, the fact that paraxial optics can help
solve problems often becomes lost on people because they never
actually build anything for the purpose of imaging. And even if a
someone never builds a camera or microscope, I think it is difficult
for them to see what paraxial optics concepts–such as principle
planes and aperture stops–can do for helping them troubleshoot their
hardware when it is not working as expected.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, with this in mind, I will use this part in a series of blog posts
to answer the following question: what is the problem that paraxial
optics solves?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Paraxial optics solves the imaging problem &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" name="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The imaging problem as
I see it is simply this: &lt;b&gt;given an optical system, how can one arrange
its components to form the image of an object at a desired&lt;/b&gt; &lt;b&gt;position
and with a predictable size and orientation?&lt;/b&gt; This question has been
asked by scientists, engineers, philosophers, and others since
antiquity because we place enormous value in pictures.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To better understand this problem, I am going to step through the
parts of this statement and explain what I mean by each. First, I
mention that the imaging problem involves the use of an &lt;b&gt;optical
system&lt;/b&gt;. I have to admit that I use this term partly because it is
part of the jargon of the optical sciences, but I also think that the
word "system" nicely captures the essence of what I would like to
say. An optical system is a collection of components such as lenses,
mirrors, and prisms taken together with their mechanical supports and
arranged in a meaningful way to capture and channel light as it
travels from one place to another. Below is one example of an optical
system that most people know pretty well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align="center"&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://kmdouglass.github.io/eye.jpg" alt="eye.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  A human eye is an optical system! From &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eye#/media/File:Eye_iris.jpg"&gt;
  Peter Nóvak, Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have already mentioned that the components of an optical system can
include things we commonly associate with optics, such as lenses and
mirrors, but really no one such component is necessary to build an
optical system so long as it captures and does something with
light. For example, &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pinhole_camera"&gt;the pinhole camera&lt;/a&gt; uses nothing but a very small
hole to form images; no lens is required! Still, we usually find some
components like lenses much more frequently in optical systems than
others, and the choice of which components to use really just depends
on the specific type of imaging problem you are trying to solve.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Next in the statement of the imaging problem I say that we will be
forming an image by arranging the components of our optical system in
a clever way. Though the intuitive notion of an image is quite clear,
I think it is actually extremely difficult to formally define it. For
the purpose of this tutorial, I think it is best at this point to rely
on the intuitive idea of an image until I have developed enough
concepts to define it in terms of optical theory &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.2" name="fnr.2" class="footref" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html#fn.2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Finally, the imaging problem involves determining the location, size,
and orientation of an image formed by the system. This means that
rearrangement of our system's components is going to change these
features of the image. Things such as the size of a CCD chip or the
weight of a lens are going to place constraints on the values these
properties can take.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-3" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-3"&gt;Perfect imaging systems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At this point I should stress that paraxial optics is not the only
theoretical tool for solving the imaging problem. We clearly can use
non-paraxial geometrical optics or wave optics to determine the
properties of an image formed by an optical system. However, what is
interesting is that paraxial optics is one of very few theoretical
frameworks in which a perfect image can be realized &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.3" name="fnr.3" class="footref" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html#fn.3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align="center"&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://kmdouglass.github.io/im_perfectOpticalSystems.png" alt="im_perfectOpticalSystems.png"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The above figure, which is called a &lt;a href="http://www.edmundoptics.com/TechSupport/resource_center/downloads/Anchor-Optics/GraphicalRayTracing.pdf"&gt;ray-trace diagram&lt;/a&gt;, illustrates
what I mean by a perfect imaging system. The system is represented as
a "black box" that collects light coming from a two-dimensional plane
(known as the object plane) and relays the light to another plane
known as the image plane. The whole system is considered to be
rotationally symmetric about a line called the optics axis so that I
can represent it as a two-dimensional sketch instead of requiring a
full, three-dimensional model. Finally, light is modeled as lines with
arrows denoting the direction of propagation &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.4" name="fnr.4" class="footref" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html#fn.4"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now comes the important point. Within the framework of paraxial optics
theory, it is possible to show that, given an object plane and an
image plane, one can construct an optical system consisting of
components that redirect the light rays in such a way that all the
rays leaving a point in the object plane are brought back together at
a corresponding point in the image plane. &lt;b&gt;This means that the perfect
optical system performs a one-to-one mapping of points in the object&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;b&gt;plane to points in the image plane&lt;/b&gt;. What's more, the distance
between every point in the image plane and the optics axis is
proportional to the distance between their corresponding points and
the axis in the object plane by a constant factor. This factor is
known as the &lt;b&gt;magnification&lt;/b&gt; of the system.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The way this perfect imaging system is realized within the context of
the theory is in the way the components redirect the rays coming from
the object &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.5" name="fnr.5" class="footref" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html#fn.5"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. What differentiates &lt;i&gt;paraxial&lt;/i&gt; geometrical optics from
plain old geometrical optics is the rules dictating how the
redirection occurs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One other important point is to consider what happens in imperfect
imaging systems. Once we violate the assumptions of paraxial optics so
that we no longer have a system operating within its range of
validity, we cannot perform a true, one-to-one mapping of points from
the object plane to the image plane. Instead, we find that rays coming
from a single point in the object plane cannot all be brought back
together in any image plane &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.6" name="fnr.6" class="footref" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html#fn.6"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. We could say that the image plane is
a concept that does not exist outside paraxial optics. And if the
image plane does not exist, how are we to strictly define an image
size and location?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, we can find planes in non-paraxial systems in which there
are pretty good images, and these usually correspond to the image
planes we find by applying the equations and simplifications of
paraxial optics. So paraxial optics is often our first tool for
modeling an imaging system. It tells us roughly where our images will
be formed and how big they are, but it will not tell us about image
quality.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-4" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-4"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With this tutorial I hope to have provided you with a conceptual basis
for understanding paraxial geometrical optics without including too
many of its details. I think a conceptual basis such as this is much
better than diving right into ray-trace diagrams with lenses and
mirros. I think new students to optics often wonder what the
importance is of paraxial optics and why it is needed when more
complete optical descriptions exist. I hope that the discussion of the
perfect imaging system and its existence only within the framework of
paraxial geometrical optics helped to clarify its importance.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" name="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p class="footpara"&gt;
You didn't expect me to give you the answer right away, did
you? :)
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.2" name="fn.2" class="footnum" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html#fnr.2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p class="footpara"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Image"&gt;Even the Wikipedia entry on the concept of an Image&lt;/a&gt; is a bit vague
and philosophical.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.3" name="fn.3" class="footnum" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html#fnr.3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p class="footpara"&gt;
Maxwell's Fisheye lens is another, but it is a good deal more
complicated and, to my knowledge, has not been demonstrated at optical
wavelengths.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.4" name="fn.4" class="footnum" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html#fnr.4"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p class="footpara"&gt;
It's important to realize that we are modeling the propagation of
light as a ray; we are not saying that light &lt;i&gt;is&lt;/i&gt; a ray. If light
really was a ray and not an electromagnetic wave, then we would not
need the wave theory of optics to explain phenomena like
diffraction. Within the framework of the axioms of geometrical optics,
a ray adequately describes how light propagates.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.5" name="fn.5" class="footnum" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html#fnr.5"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p class="footpara"&gt;
More specifically, it lies in the linearization of Snell's law,
but I won't get into that yet.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.6" name="fn.6" class="footnum" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html#fnr.6"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p class="footpara"&gt;
This phenomenon is precisely what an optical aberration is within
geometrical optics theory.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>optics</category><category>tutorials</category><guid>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2015 13:37:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Can my laser beam be collimated?</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/can-my-beam-be-collimated.html</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
The fluorescence microscopy setup in my lab requires quite a bit of
power. The minimum irradiance requirement is greater than 1 kW per
square centimeter, and this must cover an area spanning a few tens of
microns across after focusing through the objective. When I was
designing the setup, the highest priority was placed on finding a
cheap laser with as much power as possible at a wavelength of 647 nm;
I considered all other qualities of the laser of secondary importance.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Just like everything else in science, I have learned a very good
lesson from this experience. The laser I decided to purchase is a &lt;a href="http://www.omicron-laser.de/english/lasers/diode-lasers/brixx-lasers/brixx-diode-lasers.html"&gt;800
mW BrixX laser from Omicron&lt;/a&gt;. The cost is under $10,000, which I
consider to be a pretty good deal for the amount of power it puts
out. There is no fiber-coupled version, but all of our lasers are free
space anyway so I did not consider this to be a big problem. The beam
is astigmatic, which is to be expected from a high power laser diode.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The astigmatism is not necessarily a big problem for me, though. What
is surprising to me is how difficult it is to keep the beam &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Collimated_light"&gt;collimated&lt;/a&gt;
over large distances, that is, to keep it roughly the same size as it
propagates. My application requires a fairly small beam size since the
exit pupil of the objective is only 6 millimeters in diameter. With
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M_squared"&gt;M-squared&lt;/a&gt; values direct from the laser of 12 and 25, it is quite
difficult to keep the beam collimated for a long enough distance to
steer the beam through all the optics and to keep it small enough to
prevent overfilling the objective's exit pupil and losing power.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What I have learned from this is that free-space diode lasers, and
more generally multimode laser beams, require extra consideration to
ensure that they will stay collimated in long setups.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, how can I predict the distance over which my beam can stay
collimated to better judge how well it will work for my setup? The
first thing to realize is that no beam can stay collimated
forever. Real laser beams experience diffraction, which causes them to
spread as they propagate. This means that the first thing I should do
is to consider the distances spanned by the beam paths. In a
microscopy setup, this path will probably not be longer than a couple
meters. In mine, it's roughly two meters since I am combining a number
of laser beams together and need the extra space.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Once I identify the length scale over which the beam should stay
collimated, I need to examine the beam parameter that is best
associated with collimation. For a pure Gaussian beam, this parameter
is the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rayleigh_length"&gt;Rayleigh range&lt;/a&gt;. The Rayleigh range is the distance between the
beam waist and the point where the cross-sectional area of the beam
has doubled, or, equivalently, to the point where the radius of the
beam has increased over the waist radius by a factor of the
\(\sqrt{2}\). For a pure Gaussian beam with a waist radius of \(w_0\) and
a wavelength of \(\lambda\), the Rayleigh range is given by the equation
&lt;/p&gt;


\begin{equation*}
z_R = \frac{\pi w_0^2}{\lambda}
\end{equation*}

&lt;p&gt;
It is represented by the symbol &lt;i&gt;z&lt;sub&gt;R&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/i&gt; in the figure below from
Wikipedia. The total distance over which the beam will stay collimated
is represented by &lt;i&gt;b&lt;/i&gt; and is just twice the Rayleigh range.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align="center"&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://kmdouglass.github.io/GaussianBeamWaist.png" alt="GaussianBeamWaist.png"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The Rayleigh range of a Gaussian laser beam should therefore be larger
than the characteristic distance of my setup that I identified in the
previous step. But what about multimode beams like the one from my
laser diode? This is where the concept of an "embedded Gaussian" comes
into play. (For more information about this idea, see &lt;a href="http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.177.3400&amp;amp;rep=rep1&amp;amp;type=pdf"&gt;this tutorial by
Tony Siegman&lt;/a&gt;.) I can predict the collimated distance by computing the
Rayleigh range of an ideal Gaussian beam, and then divide it by the
M&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; parameter for the beam.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's take an example using numbers from my own laser. I will first
pretend there are no collimating optics in the laser, which is not
true but will serve as a good example as to why diode lasers without
collimating optics are not good for free space setups. From the
laser's spec sheet, I know that the M&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; value in the ``bad'' direction
is 25 and that its waist size, which is probably half the size of the
diode in one principle direction, is 107 microns. Using the above
equation, I get a value of 56 centimeters, which means that an ideal
Gaussian beam with these specs will stay collimated over about half a
meter.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
However, my real multimode beam will have a Rayleigh range that is
smaller than this value by a factor of 25, which is only about 2
centimeters. For this reason, diode laser beams almost always have
collimating optics; the beam from the diode itself is highly
divergent.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Returning to my own setup, if I resize the beam using a telescope to
have a waist radius of 2 millimeters so it almost entirely fits inside
the objective's exit pupil, the Rayleigh range of the embedded
Gaussian beam will be almost &lt;i&gt;20 meters&lt;/i&gt;, which is pretty long. The
real beam, however, will have a Rayleigh range of about 780
millimeters meters due to the high M&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; value. &lt;b&gt;Practically, this means
I have about one meter of collimated laser beam&lt;/b&gt; with which to work
since I have double the Rayleigh range of collimated distance, but
really I want the beam to travel less distance than this.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Fortunately I can shrink the beam path enough that this should not be
a problem, but it does serve as a very good lesson when looking for
lasers for a microscopy application.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>microscopy</category><category>optics</category><guid>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/can-my-beam-be-collimated.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2015 07:44:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Relearning paraxial optics</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/relearning-paraxial-optics.html</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
As a microscopist who designs and builds custom microscopes, I often
find that first order ray tracing is one of the most useful tools I
have. It is most useful to me when I am starting a design or for
checking that I have not made any serious logical blunders when
working at the bench. I also find it to be a good teaching tool and
excellent for communicating my designs to others.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Since I have recently made a lot of back-of-the-envelope ray trace
designs for a microscope I am building at work, I have begun to
critically think about why ray tracing works so well and how it fits
inside the structure of the physical theories of optics.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Ray tracing is a technique derived from &lt;b&gt;paraxial geometrical optics&lt;/b&gt;
and really is just a consequence of the axioms and assumptions in the
development of the theory. When I think back to when I first learned
about paraxial optics, however, I am reminded of severe assumptions
that place limits on the scope of its validity. So how can a theory
that makes such an enormous simplification by treating the
electromagnetic waves described by Maxwell's equations as lines
obeying the rules of geometry still be so useful?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In this next series of blog posts, I want to explore this question and
take the time to relearn paraxial optics with the benefit of
hindsight. Physicists typically learn paraxial optics as their first
theory of optics because it is relatively easy as compared to
electromagnetism and quantum optics. I am curious what aspects of the
theory I can appreciate now that I am familiar with the more advanced
optical theories.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The picture below might also provide a bit of motivation for why this
interests me: we physicists learn about optics theories in a direction
of increasing complexity during our education. However, this approach
also means that we learn the most general theories last, so it is not
obvious why assumptions and approximations are made in the theories we
learn first. The result, I think, leads to a bit of logical
discordance in our minds that can prevent a clear understanding of the
subject. With this series of posts I hope to remove this cognitive
dissonance and improve my understanding of the field I work in.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://kmdouglass.github.io/order_of_optics_theories.png" alt="order_of_optics_theories.png"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>optics</category><category>tutorials</category><guid>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/relearning-paraxial-optics.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2015 09:05:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Parallelized confocal microscopy with multiply scattered light</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/confocal-by-scattering.html</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
My PhD work dealt with the topic of sensing and imaging using light
that had been transmitted through a random medium. This topic is
often applied to practical problems such as imaging through a
turbulent atmosphere or detecting objects, like a tumor, buried
beneath an opaque substance, like skin and muscle tissue. Though I
don't necessarily work in this field anymore, I still follow its
developments occasionally.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A few articles appeared within the last week in journals like &lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/nphoton/journal/v8/n10/full/nphoton.2014.189.html"&gt;Nature&lt;/a&gt;
Photonics]] about the problem of imaging through walls. This problem
has been studied since the late 1980's in a number of papers,
including the notable &lt;a href="http://journals.aps.org/prl/abstract/10.1103/PhysRevLett.61.834"&gt;Feng, Kane, Lee, and Stone&lt;/a&gt; paper and &lt;a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/037596019090615U#"&gt;Freund's
discussion&lt;/a&gt; of using cross-correlating two speckle patterns, one of
which is a reference wave, to do a sort of holographic imaging. The
recent work continues from these original ideas and applies them to
microscopy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One article appeared on the arXiv and is from the &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1410.2079"&gt;Mosk and Lagendijk&lt;/a&gt;
camp. In this article, they exploit the optical memory effect,
whereby a speckle pattern generated by the multiple scattering of a
plane wave by a random slab is simply translated as the angle of
incidence of the plane wave is varied. If a thin fluorescent target
is placed directly on the opposite face of the scattering slab, it
will be excited by the speckle pattern and emit a fluorescence
signal that can be captured by an objective. Changing the angle of
incidence of the plane wave then allows for multiple points to scan
the sample in parallel. Ultimately, a number of images are taken
with the sample illuminated by several transversally shifted speckle
patterns and the resulting 4D data cube (corresponding to the
sample's x-y dimensions and the two tilt angles of the incident
plane wave) is used to render an image with improved resolution.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As stated in the article's title, the resolution improvement is
relative to that of a widefield microscope. They obtain an effective
point spread function of about 140 nm and a field of view of 10
microns by 10 microns.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So how does the technique work? My first thought was that the memory
effect is simply another way of saying that the speckle pattern acts
as a number of confocal-like point sources, which essentially means
this is something of a parallelized confocal microscope. However,
I'm not sure this is correct for two reasons: 1) there is no
detection pin hole, and 2) the angle of incidence of the plane wave
is scanned over a small angular range so that the speckle pattern is
simply translated. If the angle of incidence is so great that the
linear change in phase of the plane wave is greater than roughly the
size of the scattering slab, the speckle pattern is no longer simply
translated but changes completely.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In reality, the ultimate resolution of this technique is the average
speckle grain size, which can't be less than about half the
wavelength. This suggests that the angular spectrum of the speckle
pattern is what determines the resolution improvement.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The speckle pattern in a region bounded by the maximum extent of the
memory effect has a fixed angular spectrum and translating the
speckle pattern only changes the phase of the spectrum. So, scanning
a target with a speckle pattern produces beat patterns containing
high spatial frequency information that can propgate on the low
spatial frequency waves that reach the objective. Translating the
speckle pattern then performs a sort of phase-shifting
interferometry that allows for both intensity and phase retrieval of
the object.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Importantly, if the speckle pattern is scanned outside the range of
the memory effect, the speckle's angular spectrum within the region
changes completely so that the original reference wave is lost. The
fact that the object is fluorescent and not simply scattering the
light shouldn't matter if the fluorescence intensity is linear with
the excitation light intensity. However, if the fluorescence has
saturated at the average intensity of the speckle pattern, then I'm
not exactly sure that this technique will work (though maybe some
sort of nonlinear structured illumination microscopy could be
achieved).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Overall it's a neat demonstration and worth the exercise to
understand it, though I'm doubtful that at this point it would be
useful for applications in the life sciences. This is because the
resolution isn't that much better than a spinning disk confocal
microscope, which has a larger field of view and would arguably be
easier to use by biologists.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>microscopy</category><category>optics</category><guid>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/confocal-by-scattering.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2014 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>An accidental half-wave plate</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/half-wave plate.html</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Recently in the lab we made a seemingly minor change to one of our
microscopes that led to a minor problem that lasted for about a
week. Briefly, we introduced a mirror following a periscope that
raises the plane that the laser beams travel in parallel to the
table. The periscope is necessary to bringthe beams out of the plane
containing the beam-combining optics and into the TIRF module port
on our Zeiss inverted microscope for epi-illumination.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We had introduced the mirror to give us one more degree of freedom
for steering the beam, but to do so we had to move the periscope and
turn one of the mirrors by 90 degrees. Unfortunately, after doing
this we found that the optical power leaving the microscope
objective had dropped by a factor of 10, which was insufficient to
do STORM imaging.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We eventually determined that the Zeiss TIRF module contained a
polarizing beam splitter that combined the laser beams with white
light from another port at 90 degrees to the beam path. In the
newsetup, we placed a broadband halfwave plate before the TIRF
module, rotated it while watching a power meter, and were finally
able to get even more power leaving the objective than with the old
setup.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So what had happened to cause the decrease in power by adding
another mirror, and why did introducing the halfwave plate fix the
problem? As it turns out, you can rotate the polarization by 90
degrees using only a pair of mirrors to redirect the beam into a
plane parallel to its original plane of travel but into a direction
perpendicular to its original one. This was what we were doing
before we introduced the mirror. After the new mirror was put in
place, we rotated a mirror of the periscope, which effectively
rotated the laser beam's polarization back into its original
orientation. And, since there was a polarizing beam splitter inside
the TIRF module, the new beam polarization was transmitted through
the module instead of being reflected towards the objective.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The picture below describes how this can happen. Note that the final
beam trajectory is in the direction pointing &lt;i&gt;into&lt;/i&gt; the screen.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://kmdouglass.github.io/images/polarization_rotator.png" alt="polarization_rotator.png"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>optics</category><guid>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/half-wave plate.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2014 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The art of alignment</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/alignment.html</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I've been working on realigning one of our STORM microscopy setups
and moving the other over the past couple weeks. As a result, I've
been doing a lot more alignment lately than I normally do, which has
got me thinking about alignment in general.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've worked in optics labs for nearly ten years now, but I was never
systematically taught how to do alignments. Eventually, I just
figured it out from asking and watching lots of others do it. This
part of experimental optics seems to be something that's passed down
and shared across generations of PhD students and post-docs, like
some sort of cultural heritage preserved by spoken word.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Unfortunately, this fact means that written tutorials or alternative
resources on alignment are scarce. This in turn leads to frustration
for new students who can't easily find someone to show them how to
align a system. I was lucky in my training because both my
undergraduate and graduate programs were in centers dedicated to the
study of optics and optical engineering. Resources were
plentiful. But for a biologist working with a custom microscope
using multiple laser lines, finding someone who is competent in
optics to help realign their system can be highly unlikely.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So how can people who don't have a background in optics be trained
in alignment? I'm certain that written tutorials are &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; the best
tool, since aligning an optics setup is a very hands-on job. But, a
tutorial that makes explicit the principles of alignment might make
a good starting point for others.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What are these principles? Below is my rough, initial list that
applies to aligning laser beams. Aligning incoherent systems is
another beast altogether.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The angle of the beam propagation is just as important as the
position of the beam in a plane perpendicular to the table. In
other words, just because a beam is going through a stopped-down
iris doesn't mean it's traveling where you think it is.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to measure the beam position in two planes to determine
its angle of propagation.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use "layers of abstraction" to divide sections of the setup into
independent units.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use paired mirrors to get enough degrees of freedom to establish
these abstraction layers.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design feedback mechanisms into the system. In other words, keep
some irises or alignment marks on the walls in place to aid in
future realignments.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description><category>optics</category><guid>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/alignment.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2014 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>