<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Kyle M. Douglass (optics)</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link rel="self" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/categories/optics.xml" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2014 14:26:54 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Parallelized confocal microscopy with multiply scattered light</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/confocal-by-scattering.html</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
My PhD work dealt with the topic of sensing and imaging using light
that had been transmitted through a random medium. This topic is
often applied to practical problems such as imaging through a
turbulent atmosphere or detecting objects, like a tumor, buried
beneath an opaque substance, like skin and muscle tissue. Though I
don't necessarily work in this field anymore, I still follow its
developments occasionally.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A few articles appeared within the last week in journals like &lt;a href="http://www.nature.com/nphoton/journal/v8/n10/full/nphoton.2014.189.html"&gt;Nature&lt;/a&gt;
Photonics]] about the problem of imaging through walls. This problem
has been studied since the late 1980's in a number of papers,
including the notable &lt;a href="http://journals.aps.org/prl/abstract/10.1103/PhysRevLett.61.834"&gt;Feng, Kane, Lee, and Stone&lt;/a&gt; paper and &lt;a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/037596019090615U#"&gt;Freund's
discussion&lt;/a&gt; of using cross-correlating two speckle patterns, one of
which is a reference wave, to do a sort of holographic imaging. The
recent work continues from these original ideas and applies them to
microscopy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One article appeared on the arXiv and is from the &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1410.2079"&gt;Mosk and Lagendijk&lt;/a&gt;
camp. In this article, they exploit the optical memory effect,
whereby a speckle pattern generated by the multiple scattering of a
plane wave by a random slab is simply translated as the angle of
incidence of the plane wave is varied. If a thin fluorescent target
is placed directly on the opposite face of the scattering slab, it
will be excited by the speckle pattern and emit a fluorescence
signal that can be captured by an objective. Changing the angle of
incidence of the plane wave then allows for multiple points to scan
the sample in parallel. Ultimately, a number of images are taken
with the sample illuminated by several transversally shifted speckle
patterns and the resulting 4D data cube (corresponding to the
sample's x-y dimensions and the two tilt angles of the incident
plane wave) is used to render an image with improved resolution.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As stated in the article's title, the resolution improvement is
relative to that of a widefield microscope. They obtain an effective
point spread function of about 140 nm and a field of view of 10
microns by 10 microns.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So how does the technique work? My first thought was that the memory
effect is simply another way of saying that the speckle pattern acts
as a number of confocal-like point sources, which essentially means
this is something of a parallelized confocal microscope. However,
I'm not sure this is correct for two reasons: 1) there is no
detection pin hole, and 2) the angle of incidence of the plane wave
is scanned over a small angular range so that the speckle pattern is
simply translated. If the angle of incidence is so great that the
linear change in phase of the plane wave is greater than roughly the
size of the scattering slab, the speckle pattern is no longer simply
translated but changes completely.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In reality, the ultimate resolution of this technique is the average
speckle grain size, which can't be less than about half the
wavelength. This suggests that the angular spectrum of the speckle
pattern is what determines the resolution improvement.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The speckle pattern in a region bounded by the maximum extent of the
memory effect has a fixed angular spectrum and translating the
speckle pattern only changes the phase of the spectrum. So, scanning
a target with a speckle pattern produces beat patterns containing
high spatial frequency information that can propgate on the low
spatial frequency waves that reach the objective. Translating the
speckle pattern then performs a sort of phase-shifting
interferometry that allows for both intensity and phase retrieval of
the object.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Importantly, if the speckle pattern is scanned outside the range of
the memory effect, the speckle's angular spectrum within the region
changes completely so that the original reference wave is lost. The
fact that the object is fluorescent and not simply scattering the
light shouldn't matter if the fluorescence intensity is linear with
the excitation light intensity. However, if the fluorescence has
saturated at the average intensity of the speckle pattern, then I'm
not exactly sure that this technique will work (though maybe some
sort of nonlinear structured illumination microscopy could be
achieved).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Overall it's a neat demonstration and worth the exercise to
understand it, though I'm doubtful that at this point it would be
useful for applications in the life sciences. This is because the
resolution isn't that much better than a spinning disk confocal
microscope, which has a larger field of view and would arguably be
easier to use by biologists.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>microscopy</category><category>optics</category><guid>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/confocal-by-scattering.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2014 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>An accidental half-wave plate</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/half-wave plate.html</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Recently in the lab we made a seemingly minor change to one of our
microscopes that led to a minor problem that lasted for about a
week. Briefly, we introduced a mirror following a periscope that
raises the plane that the laser beams travel in parallel to the
table. The periscope is necessary to bringthe beams out of the plane
containing the beam-combining optics and into the TIRF module port
on our Zeiss inverted microscope for epi-illumination.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We had introduced the mirror to give us one more degree of freedom
for steering the beam, but to do so we had to move the periscope and
turn one of the mirrors by 90 degrees. Unfortunately, after doing
this we found that the optical power leaving the microscope
objective had dropped by a factor of 10, which was insufficient to
do STORM imaging.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We eventually determined that the Zeiss TIRF module contained a
polarizing beam splitter that combined the laser beams with white
light from another port at 90 degrees to the beam path. In the
newsetup, we placed a broadband halfwave plate before the TIRF
module, rotated it while watching a power meter, and were finally
able to get even more power leaving the objective than with the old
setup.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So what had happened to cause the decrease in power by adding
another mirror, and why did introducing the halfwave plate fix the
problem? As it turns out, you can rotate the polarization by 90
degrees using only a pair of mirrors to redirect the beam into a
plane parallel to its original plane of travel but into a direction
perpendicular to its original one. This was what we were doing
before we introduced the mirror. After the new mirror was put in
place, we rotated a mirror of the periscope, which effectively
rotated the laser beam's polarization back into its original
orientation. And, since there was a polarizing beam splitter inside
the TIRF module, the new beam polarization was transmitted through
the module instead of being reflected towards the objective.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The picture below describes how this can happen. Note that the final
beam trajectory is in the direction pointing &lt;i&gt;into&lt;/i&gt; the screen.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://kmdouglass.github.io/images/polarization_rotator.png" alt="polarization_rotator.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>optics</category><guid>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/half-wave plate.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2014 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The art of alignment</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/alignment.html</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I've been working on realigning one of our STORM microscopy setups
and moving the other over the past couple weeks. As a result, I've
been doing a lot more alignment lately than I normally do, which has
got me thinking about alignment in general.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I've worked in optics labs for nearly ten years now, but I was never
systematically taught how to do alignments. Eventually, I just
figured it out from asking and watching lots of others do it. This
part of experimental optics seems to be something that's passed down
and shared across generations of PhD students and post-docs, like
some sort of cultural heritage preserved by spoken word.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Unfortunately, this fact means that written tutorials or alternative
resources on alignment are scarce. This in turn leads to frustration
for new students who can't easily find someone to show them how to
align a system. I was lucky in my training because both my
undergraduate and graduate programs were in centers dedicated to the
study of optics and optical engineering. Resources were
plentiful. But for a biologist working with a custom microscope
using multiple laser lines, finding someone who is competent in
optics to help realign their system can be highly unlikely.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So how can people who don't have a background in optics be trained
in alignment? I'm certain that written tutorials are &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; the best
tool, since aligning an optics setup is a very hands-on job. But, a
tutorial that makes explicit the principles of alignment might make
a good starting point for others.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What are these principles? Below is my rough, initial list that
applies to aligning laser beams. Aligning incoherent systems is
another beast altogether.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;&lt;li&gt;The angle of the beam propagation is just as important as the
position of the beam in a plane perpendicular to the table. In
other words, just because a beam is going through a stopped-down
iris doesn't mean it's traveling where you think it is.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to measure the beam position in two planes to determine
its angle of propagation.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use "layers of abstraction" to divide sections of the setup into
independent units.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use paired mirrors to get enough degrees of freedom to establish
these abstraction layers.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design feedback mechanisms into the system. In other words, keep
some irises or alignment marks on the walls in place to aid in
future realignments.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description><category>optics</category><guid>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/alignment.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2014 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>