<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Kyle M. Douglass (super-resolution)</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/categories/super-resolution.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2014 18:10:30 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Measurements as processes</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/measurements.html</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I work in microscopy, which is one form of optical sensing. In the
sensing field, we are often concerned with making measurements on
some structure so as to learn what it is. Often, I think the word
measurement refers to the dataset that's produced.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think it can be more effective to think of a measurement as a
process that transforms the structure into the dataset. Why is this
so? Well, to understand what the original structure was, we have to
look at our data and make an inference. If we understand the steps
in the process that took the original structure and turned it into
data, we can apply the inverse of those steps in reverse order to
get the original structure.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, our dataset may only capture some limited aspects of the
original structure, so we may only be able to make probabilistic
statements about what the original structure was.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Take, for example, super-resolution microscopy experiments (SR). In
SR, some feature of a cell is labeled with a discrete number of
fluorescent molecules, then these molecules are localized to a high
precision. The centroids of all the molecules are then convolved
with a Gaussian function (or something similar) with a width equal
to the localization precision to produce a rendered, super-resolved
image of the structure. The measurement process can be thought of
like this:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;&lt;li&gt;Attach fluorescent molecules to every macromolecule (or randomly
to a subset of macromolecules) in the structure of interest.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For every molecule that emits photons during the time of
acqusition by one camera frame, record its true coordinate
positions and the number of detected photons. This can create
multiple localizations that correspond to the same molecule in
multiple camera frames.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove molecules from the lis that emitted less than some
threshold number of photons. These correspond to molecules with a
signal-to-noise ratio that is too low to be detected.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Randomly bump the molecule positions according to a Gaussian
distribution with width equal to the localization precision in
each direction.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;
This process results in a list of molecule positions that originally
were located on the structure of interest, but were eventually
displaced randomly and filtered out due to various sources of
noise. To understand what the original structure was, we have to
"undo" each of these steps to the best of our abilities.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think it's interesting to note that everytime a random change to
the original molecule positions occurred, we lose some information
about the structure.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>sensing</category><category>super-resolution</category><guid>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/measurements.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 18 Dec 2014 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>