<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Kyle M. Douglass (Switzerland)</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link type="application/rss+xml" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/categories/switzerland.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2016 18:19:10 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Thoughts from the Swiss Photonics Machine Learning Workshop</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/thoughts-from-the-swiss-photonics-machine-learning-workshop.html</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
Today I attended a &lt;a href="http://www.swissphotonics.net/workshops/workshop-datenbank?2886"&gt;machine learning workshop hosted by Swiss
Photonics&lt;/a&gt;. The workshop was a small, day-long series of talks by
industry experts in Neuchâtel, Switzerland, not far from Lausanne. I
went to the workshop because a) I don't know much about machine
learning and want to know more, and b) I wanted to connect with people
within the Swiss Photonics circle. Most of the talks concerned deep
learning for solving problems in industrial machine vision
applications, such as quality control for the watch-making industry.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Here are the main things I learned, which may or not be correct. I
welcome any opinions or corrections in the comments:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The term "learning" is used to mean "teaching a computer to
recognize and classify patterns in data", such as finding people in
images.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning involves finding patterns in data. Once patterns are
idenfitied, a set of them can be combined to form a model. A model
makes predictions about what future data may look like. This means
that a model may be used to see whether new data meets our
expectations. An example would be using pictures of products from a
production line and searching for defects, i.e. those products that
don't fit our classification of "good" products.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning applications require lots of training data to
implement. This is where the primary cost of applying learning
algorithms comes from.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are three categories of learning: supervised, reinforced, and
unsupervised.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The value in neural networks is their ability to make decisions in a
way that is similar to humans. Other classification and decision
algorithms work using strict programmatic rules and look for
user-specified features. Neural networks do not require domain
knowledge to establish features for a classifier. Their generality
is their strength.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deep_learning"&gt;Deep learning&lt;/a&gt; just refers to really big neural networks. Neural
networks are not new; recent hardware advances like GPU-based
computation and the availability of large datasets are what has
enabled Deep learning.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I did not hear much discussion about the tradeoffs and downsides to
using neural networks or deep learning, other than that they require
large amounts of training data. Notable talks were given by Reto Wyss
of &lt;a href="http://www.vidi-systems.com/company/about-us.html"&gt;ViDi&lt;/a&gt; and Virginie Moser of &lt;a href="http://www.csem.ch/site/"&gt;CSEM&lt;/a&gt;. Wyss very eloquently explained
why deep learning is useful for classification. Moser presented an
extremely small and light-weight embedded machine vision system for
traffic light control.
&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>machine learning</category><category>photonics</category><category>Switzerland</category><guid>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/thoughts-from-the-swiss-photonics-machine-learning-workshop.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2016 17:31:32 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>