<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Kyle M. Douglass (tutorials)</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/categories/tutorials.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2016 15:12:06 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Paraxial Optics (2): What problem does it solve?</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-1" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-1"&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-1"&gt;
&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paraxial optics is a tool to aid in building optical systems.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paraxial optics solves the imaging problem.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The imaging problem concerns finding the location, size, and
orientation of an image given an object and an optical system.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An optical system is a collection of objects like lenses, mirrors,
prisms, cameras, etc. that collects the light emitted or scattered
by an object and delivers it to another location where it can be
detected and processed for information.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The rules of paraxial optics allow for a perfect imaging system,
i.e. a system that creates a one-to-one correspondance between
points in an object plane and an image plane.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-2" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-2"&gt;Paraxial optics solves the imaging problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;In this post I will use paraxial optics to mean paraxial geometrical
optics. This is important since the paraxial approximation can also&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;i&gt;apply to the wave theory of light.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
When learning a new theory, I often find it most useful to first
identify the problem that the theory was developed to solve. This
approach is particularly pertinent for learning paraxial optics, since
the theory is largely used as a tool to aid in the construction of
optical systems. Unfortunately, the fact that paraxial optics can help
solve problems often becomes lost on people because they never
actually build anything for the purpose of imaging. And even if a
someone never builds a camera or microscope, I think it is difficult
for them to see what paraxial optics concepts–such as principle
planes and aperture stops–can do for helping them troubleshoot their
hardware when it is not working as expected.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, with this in mind, I will use this part in a series of blog posts
to answer the following question: what is the problem that paraxial
optics solves?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Paraxial optics solves the imaging problem &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" name="fnr.1" class="footref" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The imaging problem as
I see it is simply this: &lt;b&gt;given an optical system, how can one arrange
its components to form the image of an object at a desired&lt;/b&gt; &lt;b&gt;position
and with a predictable size and orientation?&lt;/b&gt; This question has been
asked by scientists, engineers, philosophers, and others since
antiquity because we place enormous value in pictures.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To better understand this problem, I am going to step through the
parts of this statement and explain what I mean by each. First, I
mention that the imaging problem involves the use of an &lt;b&gt;optical
system&lt;/b&gt;. I have to admit that I use this term partly because it is
part of the jargon of the optical sciences, but I also think that the
word "system" nicely captures the essence of what I would like to
say. An optical system is a collection of components such as lenses,
mirrors, and prisms taken together with their mechanical supports and
arranged in a meaningful way to capture and channel light as it
travels from one place to another. Below is one example of an optical
system that most people know pretty well.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align="center"&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://kmdouglass.github.io/eye.jpg" alt="eye.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

  A human eye is an optical system! From &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eye#/media/File:Eye_iris.jpg"&gt;
  Peter Nóvak, Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I have already mentioned that the components of an optical system can
include things we commonly associate with optics, such as lenses and
mirrors, but really no one such component is necessary to build an
optical system so long as it captures and does something with
light. For example, &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pinhole_camera"&gt;the pinhole camera&lt;/a&gt; uses nothing but a very small
hole to form images; no lens is required! Still, we usually find some
components like lenses much more frequently in optical systems than
others, and the choice of which components to use really just depends
on the specific type of imaging problem you are trying to solve.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Next in the statement of the imaging problem I say that we will be
forming an image by arranging the components of our optical system in
a clever way. Though the intuitive notion of an image is quite clear,
I think it is actually extremely difficult to formally define it. For
the purpose of this tutorial, I think it is best at this point to rely
on the intuitive idea of an image until I have developed enough
concepts to define it in terms of optical theory &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.2" name="fnr.2" class="footref" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html#fn.2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Finally, the imaging problem involves determining the location, size,
and orientation of an image formed by the system. This means that
rearrangement of our system's components is going to change these
features of the image. Things such as the size of a CCD chip or the
weight of a lens are going to place constraints on the values these
properties can take.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-3" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-3"&gt;Perfect imaging systems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At this point I should stress that paraxial optics is not the only
theoretical tool for solving the imaging problem. We clearly can use
non-paraxial geometrical optics or wave optics to determine the
properties of an image formed by an optical system. However, what is
interesting is that paraxial optics is one of very few theoretical
frameworks in which a perfect image can be realized &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.3" name="fnr.3" class="footref" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html#fn.3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align="center"&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://kmdouglass.github.io/im_perfectOpticalSystems.png" alt="im_perfectOpticalSystems.png"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The above figure, which is called a &lt;a href="http://www.edmundoptics.com/TechSupport/resource_center/downloads/Anchor-Optics/GraphicalRayTracing.pdf"&gt;ray-trace diagram&lt;/a&gt;, illustrates
what I mean by a perfect imaging system. The system is represented as
a "black box" that collects light coming from a two-dimensional plane
(known as the object plane) and relays the light to another plane
known as the image plane. The whole system is considered to be
rotationally symmetric about a line called the optics axis so that I
can represent it as a two-dimensional sketch instead of requiring a
full, three-dimensional model. Finally, light is modeled as lines with
arrows denoting the direction of propagation &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.4" name="fnr.4" class="footref" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html#fn.4"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now comes the important point. Within the framework of paraxial optics
theory, it is possible to show that, given an object plane and an
image plane, one can construct an optical system consisting of
components that redirect the light rays in such a way that all the
rays leaving a point in the object plane are brought back together at
a corresponding point in the image plane. &lt;b&gt;This means that the perfect
optical system performs a one-to-one mapping of points in the object&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;b&gt;plane to points in the image plane&lt;/b&gt;. What's more, the distance
between every point in the image plane and the optics axis is
proportional to the distance between their corresponding points and
the axis in the object plane by a constant factor. This factor is
known as the &lt;b&gt;magnification&lt;/b&gt; of the system.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The way this perfect imaging system is realized within the context of
the theory is in the way the components redirect the rays coming from
the object &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.5" name="fnr.5" class="footref" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html#fn.5"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. What differentiates &lt;i&gt;paraxial&lt;/i&gt; geometrical optics from
plain old geometrical optics is the rules dictating how the
redirection occurs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One other important point is to consider what happens in imperfect
imaging systems. Once we violate the assumptions of paraxial optics so
that we no longer have a system operating within its range of
validity, we cannot perform a true, one-to-one mapping of points from
the object plane to the image plane. Instead, we find that rays coming
from a single point in the object plane cannot all be brought back
together in any image plane &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.6" name="fnr.6" class="footref" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html#fn.6"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. We could say that the image plane is
a concept that does not exist outside paraxial optics. And if the
image plane does not exist, how are we to strictly define an image
size and location?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, we can find planes in non-paraxial systems in which there
are pretty good images, and these usually correspond to the image
planes we find by applying the equations and simplifications of
paraxial optics. So paraxial optics is often our first tool for
modeling an imaging system. It tells us roughly where our images will
be formed and how big they are, but it will not tell us about image
quality.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-sec-4" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="sec-4"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With this tutorial I hope to have provided you with a conceptual basis
for understanding paraxial geometrical optics without including too
many of its details. I think a conceptual basis such as this is much
better than diving right into ray-trace diagrams with lenses and
mirros. I think new students to optics often wonder what the
importance is of paraxial optics and why it is needed when more
complete optical descriptions exist. I hope that the discussion of the
perfect imaging system and its existence only within the framework of
paraxial geometrical optics helped to clarify its importance.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="footnotes"&gt;
&lt;h2 class="footnotes"&gt;Footnotes: &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id="text-footnotes"&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.1" name="fn.1" class="footnum" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html#fnr.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p class="footpara"&gt;
You didn't expect me to give you the answer right away, did
you? :)
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.2" name="fn.2" class="footnum" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html#fnr.2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p class="footpara"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Image"&gt;Even the Wikipedia entry on the concept of an Image&lt;/a&gt; is a bit vague
and philosophical.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.3" name="fn.3" class="footnum" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html#fnr.3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p class="footpara"&gt;
Maxwell's Fisheye lens is another, but it is a good deal more
complicated and, to my knowledge, has not been demonstrated at optical
wavelengths.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.4" name="fn.4" class="footnum" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html#fnr.4"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p class="footpara"&gt;
It's important to realize that we are modeling the propagation of
light as a ray; we are not saying that light &lt;i&gt;is&lt;/i&gt; a ray. If light
really was a ray and not an electromagnetic wave, then we would not
need the wave theory of optics to explain phenomena like
diffraction. Within the framework of the axioms of geometrical optics,
a ray adequately describes how light propagates.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.5" name="fn.5" class="footnum" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html#fnr.5"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p class="footpara"&gt;
More specifically, it lies in the linearization of Snell's law,
but I won't get into that yet.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="footdef"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fn.6" name="fn.6" class="footnum" href="http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html#fnr.6"&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;p class="footpara"&gt;
This phenomenon is precisely what an optical aberration is within
geometrical optics theory.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>optics</category><category>tutorials</category><guid>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/paraxial-optics-2-what-problem-does-it-solve.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2015 13:37:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Relearning paraxial optics</title><link>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/relearning-paraxial-optics.html</link><dc:creator>Kyle M. Douglass</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
As a microscopist who designs and builds custom microscopes, I often
find that first order ray tracing is one of the most useful tools I
have. It is most useful to me when I am starting a design or for
checking that I have not made any serious logical blunders when
working at the bench. I also find it to be a good teaching tool and
excellent for communicating my designs to others.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Since I have recently made a lot of back-of-the-envelope ray trace
designs for a microscope I am building at work, I have begun to
critically think about why ray tracing works so well and how it fits
inside the structure of the physical theories of optics.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Ray tracing is a technique derived from &lt;b&gt;paraxial geometrical optics&lt;/b&gt;
and really is just a consequence of the axioms and assumptions in the
development of the theory. When I think back to when I first learned
about paraxial optics, however, I am reminded of severe assumptions
that place limits on the scope of its validity. So how can a theory
that makes such an enormous simplification by treating the
electromagnetic waves described by Maxwell's equations as lines
obeying the rules of geometry still be so useful?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In this next series of blog posts, I want to explore this question and
take the time to relearn paraxial optics with the benefit of
hindsight. Physicists typically learn paraxial optics as their first
theory of optics because it is relatively easy as compared to
electromagnetism and quantum optics. I am curious what aspects of the
theory I can appreciate now that I am familiar with the more advanced
optical theories.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The picture below might also provide a bit of motivation for why this
interests me: we physicists learn about optics theories in a direction
of increasing complexity during our education. However, this approach
also means that we learn the most general theories last, so it is not
obvious why assumptions and approximations are made in the theories we
learn first. The result, I think, leads to a bit of logical
discordance in our minds that can prevent a clear understanding of the
subject. With this series of posts I hope to remove this cognitive
dissonance and improve my understanding of the field I work in.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://kmdouglass.github.io/order_of_optics_theories.png" alt="order_of_optics_theories.png"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>optics</category><category>tutorials</category><guid>http://kmdouglass.github.io/posts/relearning-paraxial-optics.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2015 09:05:21 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>